Guide to the Ellis P. Leonard papers, 1951-1991
Leonard, Ellis P. papers, 1951-1991
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Ellis P. Leonard papers, 1951-1991
24-2-2645.
Leonard, Ellis P.
5.5 cubic ft.
Subject files, film, photographs and audiotape
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Material relating to Leonard's writings on veterinary medicine and veterinary history as well as photographs, slides, x-rays, and movie films of surgical procedures and of Cornell Veterinary School activities.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Ellis Leonard received his DVM degree in 1934 from the New York State College of Veterinary Medicine at Cornell University. Following graduation he worked at Kansas State University and then opened a private practice in New Jersey. In 1948 he returned to Cornell to as director of the Small Animal Clinic and remained in that position until his retirement in 1969.
Dr. Leonard is well known for his small animal work, but he is also recognized for his research and writing about the history of Cornell's veterinary college, the New York State Veterinary Medical Society, and veterinary medicine in general. After his retirement he published three books and and several articles on these topics.
Dr. Leonard died February 7, 1991 at the age of 86.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Papers include materials relating to Leonard's writings, including many articles as well as his full length works: Fundamentals of Small Animal Surgery, A Cornell Heritage, and In the James Law Tradition. There is also teaching material and information gathered about the Cornell DVM Class of 1934. Forms of material include photographs, slides, x-rays, and movie films of surgical procedures and of Cornell Veterinary School activities. Topics include small animal practice, veterinary history, surgery, and artificial insemination.
SUBJECTS
Names:
New York State College of Veterinary Medicine.
Titles:
Fundamentals of small animal surgery; A Cornell heritage: veterinary medicine, 1868-1908; In the James Law tradition, 1908-1948
Subjects:
Veterinary medicine--Study and teaching.; Pet medicine.; Veterinary surgery.; Artificial insemination.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Audio cassettes.; Film (material).
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Writings
Series II. Teaching Material
Series III. Class of 1934 Alumni Material
Series IV. Miscellaneous Audio Visual Material
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Writings
  - A Cornell Heritage
    - Bound draft (Box 1)
    - Loose draft, ca. 1978 (Box 1)
    - Galleys, ca. 1978 (Box 1)
    - Illustrations, ca. 1978 (Box 1)
    - Source Notes (Box 1)
    - Reader Reports, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Subject Files
    - Ladies Auxiliary (Box 2)
    - Catskill Game Farm (Box 2)
    - Soo Medicine (Box 2)
    - New York Broadcasting Program (Box 2)
    - Conferences of the NYSVMS (Box 2)
    - Annual Conferences - Cornell (Box 2)
    - Cornell - Honor Day (Box 2)
    - SCAVMA (Box 2)
    - NY-NJ Convention (Box 2)
    - College History - General Items (Box 2)
    - H.H. Dukes (Box 2)
    - D.W. Baker (Box 2)
    - C.E. Hayden (Box 2)
    - P.P. Levine (Box 2)
    - Sunderville (Box 2)
    - Peter Olafson (Box 2)
    - H.J. Milks (Box 2)
    - H.C. Stephenson (Box 2)
    - Veterinary Medicine in Sports (Box 2)
    - Aquatic Medicine (Box 2)
    - Veterinary History - Vet Calender (Box 2)
    - Veterinary Medicine in Ithaca (Box 2)
    - CVM History - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Veterinary History - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Daniel Salmon (Box 2)
    - CVM Faculty Memorials (Box 2)
    - World War II (Box 2)
    - Interviews with Faculty (Box 2)
    - State Society Presidents (Box 2)
    - Southern Tier Veterinary Medical Association (Box 2)
    - American College of Veterinary Surgeons (Box 2)
    - Artificial Insemination (Box 2)
    - Orthopedic Cart (Box 2)
    - Curriculum Committee (Box 2)
    - Commencement - NYSVC (Box 2)
    - Ontario Veterinary College (Box 2)
    - American Veterinary College (Box 2)
    - AVMA (Box 2)
    - New York University (Box 2)
    - Phi Zeta (Box 3)
    - Bureau of Animal Industry (Box 3)
    - Regulatory Medicine (includes meat inspection)( (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous College History (Box 3)
    - Foot and Mouth Disease (Box 3)
    - Bovine TB (Box 3)
    - Board of Examiners (Box 3)
    - NYU Alumni Association (Box 3)
    - Western New York (Box 3)
    - Central New York (Box 3)
    - Central New York Veterinary Medical Society (Box 3)
    - Genesee Valley Veterinary Medical Society (Box 3)
    - Satelites (Box 3)
    - Northern New York (Box 3)
    - Long Island (Box 3)
    - Long Island Veterinary Society (Box 3)
    - Hudson Valley (Box 3)
    - New York State College of Veterinary Medicine (Box 3)
    - Southern Tier Historical Material (Box 3)
    - Faculty - General (Box 3)
    - Faculty - General (Box 3)
    - Honors and Awards (Box 3)
    - Dynasties and Families (Box 3)
    - Military (Box 3)
    - Onandaga County (Box 3)
    - Cayuga County (Box 3)
    - Greene- Ulster County (Box 3)
    - Dutchess-Putnam County (Box 3)
    - Chataqua County (Box 3)
    - Cattaraugus County (Box 3)
    - Oneida County (Box 3)
    - Catskill Mountain (Box 3)
    - Capital District (Box 3)
    - Finger Lakes (Box 3)
    - Westchester County (Box 3)
    - Other Veterinary Organizations (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Fundamentals of Small Animal Surgery
    - Bills and Illustrations (Box 4)
    - Illustrations (Box 4)
    - Title, Dedication and Contents (Box 4)
    - Illustrations (Box 5)
    - Illustrations (Box 6)
    - Illustrations (Box 7)
    - Illustrations (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Writings
    - "History of the New York State Veterinary College" (Box 3)
    - Unidentified Bound Draft (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Papers - Folder 1 of 6 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Papers - Folder 2 of 6 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Papers - Folder 3 of 6 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Papers - Folder 4 of 6 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Papers - Folder 5 of 6 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Papers - Folder 6 of 6 (Box 4)
    - Kidney Disease (Box 4)
    - "A Backward Look" (Box 4)
    - Canine Disease (Box 4)
  - Photos - Prints for Publications
    - New York State Veterinary Medical Society (Box 1)
    - Cornell Heritage (Box 2)
    - James Law Tradition (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Series II. Teaching Material
  - Veterinary History - VET570 - Student Papers, 1966 (Box 4)
  - Veterinary History - VET570 - Student Papers, 1967 (Box 4)
  - Lecture Notes (Box 4)
- Series III. Class of 1934 Alumni Material
  - Reunions (Box 4)
  - Photos (Box 4)
- Series IV. Miscellaneous Audio Visual Material
  - Films (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous photos (Box 9)
  - Slides (Box 9)
  - Original recordings of oral history interviews with Faculty (Box 9)
SEPARATED MATERIAL
Original correspondence between Walter Long Williams and Drs. Savage and Pound have been removed and housed with the Williams collection.
Original materials relating to Simon Henry Gage have been rehoused in the Gage Family Papers.